## Charlotte J. Lambert

cjl8@illinois.edu · charlottelambert.github.io

### **Research Objective**

My research aims to make online spaces more welcoming to its users through the encouragement of healthy behaviors and improved methods of moderation. Currently, my focus is on exploring the ways in which positive feedback mechanisms on platforms like Reddit can help reinforce desirable content and support community health.

Keywords: Online communities, social computing, healthy behaviors, moderation, positive reinforcement

#### **Education**

 University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign Ph.D. in Computer Science

Advisor: Eshwar Chandrasekharan

Urbana, IL 2020-present

1

Research Interests: Social Computing, Natural Language Processing

• Vassar College
Bachelor of Arts in Computer Science, Minors in Mathematics and Italian; GPA: 3.9/4.0

Poughkeepsie, NY 2016-2020

Thesis: Temporal Exploration of the Proceedings of Old Bailey

Research Advisors: Jonathan Gordon and Jennifer Walter

#### **Publications**

• "Positive reinforcement helps breed positive behavior": Moderator Perspectives on Encouraging Desirable Behavior. CSCW 2024.

Charlotte Lambert, Frederick Choi, and Eshwar Chandrasekharan

• Creator Hearts: Investigating the Impact Positive Signals from YouTube Creators in Shaping Comment Section Behaviors. Arxiv.

Frederick Choi, Charlotte Lambert, Vinay Koshy, Sowmya Pratipati, Tue Do, Eshwar Chandrasekharan

• Quantifying the Effects of Sudden Popularity via Algorithmic Curation. ICWSM 2024.

Jackie Chan, Charlotte Lambert, Frederick Choi, Stevie Chancellor, and Eshwar Chandrasekharan

• Conversational Resilience: Quantifying and Predicting Conversational Outcomes Following Adverse Events. ICWSM 2022.

Charlotte Lambert, Ananya Rajagopal, and Eshwar Chandrasekharan

• Inter-Sense: An Investigation of Sensory Blending in Fiction. In First International Workshop on Multisensory Data & Knowledge: The 3rd Conference on Language, Data and Knowledge (2021)

Corina R. Girju and Charlotte Lambert

- **Conversation-Level Resilience.** Poster in the First Workshop on NLP for Positive Impact: ACL-IJCNLP 2021 *Charlotte Lambert* and Eshwar Chandrasekharan
- Story Immersion: Toward Fiction Synesthesia for Enhanced Reader Empathy. Presentation in Uncommon Senses Conference (2021)

Corina R. Girju and Charlotte Lambert

# Research Experience

• Graduate Research Assistant

Urbana, IL Fall 2021 - present

Department of Computer Science, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

- Advisor: Eshwar Chandrasekharan
- Area of Work: Human-Computer Interaction

#### Undergraduate Research Assistant

Department of Computer Science, Vassar College

Poughkeepsie, NY 2018-2020

- Advisor: Jonathan Gordon; Project: Computational Models of Literary Variation
- Area of Work: Natural Language Processing
- Distributed Research Experiences for Undergraduates (DREU) Intern
  Department of Computer Science, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

Urbana, IL Summer 2019

Advisor: Julia Hockenmaier; Project: Collaborative Dialogue in Minecraft

Area of Work: Natural Language Processing, Machine Learning

Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Intern

University of Southern California Institute for Creative Technologies

Los Angeles, CA Summer 2018

Advisor: Jonathan Gratch, Gale Lucas; Project: *Impact of AI on User Psychology* 

Area of Work: Artificial Intelligence

### **Professional Experience**

**Graduate Research Intern** 

San Francisco, CA

Summer 2022

Twitch Interactive, Mentor: Ruth Toner Worked on projects related to community health on the Twitch platform.

### Teaching Experience

**Intro Computing: Non-Tech (CS 105)** 

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Spring 2023, Fall 2023, Spring 2024

Teaching Assistant, Instructor: Colleen Lewis, Craig Zilles Lead lab sections; Assist in group-work during lecture; Hold weekly office hours. Discrete Math (CS 173)

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Teaching Assistant, Instructor: Benjamin Cosman

Spring 2021, Summer 2021, Fall 2022

Guide weekly group discussions; Evaluate weekly exams; Hold weekly office hours.

**Introduction to Computer Science (CS 125)** 

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Teaching Assistant, Instructor: Dr. Geoffrey Challen Co-led an optional weekly recap of course material for between 50 and 100 undergraduates.

#### Awards and Honors

Graduate Teacher Certificate, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

Spring 2024

Fall 2020

**Teacher Ranked as Excellent by Students**, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign Spring 2023, Fall 2023, Spring 2024

**C.W. Gear Outstanding Graduate Student**, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

2023

Award given to one graduate student who has demonstrated excellence in research and service.

**ICWSM 2022 Virtual Scholarship** 

2022

Scholarship awarded to virtual conference participants from underrepresented groups.

Saburo Muroga Endowed Fellowship, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

*Fellowship awarded to outstanding graduate students in computer science.* 

2020-2021

Graduated with Departmental Honors, Vassar College

Honors awarded to students nominated by the Computer Science Department for academic excellence.

**Graduated with General Honors**, Vassar College

2020

2020

Honors awarded to the top 20% of the graduating class.

Honorary Sigma Xi Nomination, Vassar College

2020

Awarded to graduating seniors nominated based upon their research accomplishments and academic record.

## Professional Service and Volunteering

Reviewer

Computer-Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW)

2024

Reviewer

International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM)

2022, 2024

Girls Who Code Co-Lead Facilitator

2021-2023

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Sub-reviewer

"AAAI-MAKE: Combining Machine Learning and Knowledge Engineering Practice," AAAI Spring Symposium 2020, Stanford University

### Languages

Italian (proficient); Spanish (reading)

# **Programming**